and this particular Tasker lesson we are
going to talk about another useful jbox
automation module which is called the
evaluation tool
now this is part of the expression
evaluation section in your standard
subset which is provided by Tosca
and this module can help us to perform
different types of comparisons whose
result will be returned as true or false
so by default your action mode would be
verified because you are performing a
verification okay
now the only thing which you need to
pass here is the expression so
expression is nothing but
um how you are going to compare two
particular values right whether it is
equals equals not equals less than
greater than so any kind of comparison
operator right and you have to use two
values through which you can make a
comparison okay and in this expression
you can use any kind of dynamic
Expressions right so you can compare a
buffer with another buffer a buffer with
a configuration parameter a buffer with
a normal or dynamic expression right so
any kind of comparison is possible and
it's a very powerful uh evaluation tool
uh which Tosca provides uh through which
you can basically perform any kind of
comparisons okay
so let's look at the Practical example
and see how we can use this evaluation
tool module in our regular automation
okay
so for this purpose uh I'm going to use
this particular application which is the
demo webshop uh my scenario is to click
on the login button and then login uh
with the email and password and then
verify whether the username is displayed
on the page or not okay
now I'm going to show you two ways of
doing this one is the generic way which
we have already learned like you uh user
action mode verify and then you use the
inner text to verify whether it matches
a particular value or not right
now what I have already done in the
background is I've already created a
module for this and I have captured all
the elements which are required or
scanned them and then I've also created
a test case with different test steps
okay now when I run this you will see
that it is going to verify uh that
particular username but it is not using
the t-box automation module it is the
first way of doing this which is the
normal verification okay which is using
the action mode verify
so let's first see this and then we will
see how we can change this around to use
the t-box evaluation module and maybe
make it more Dynamic
um then the current version of what we
have done okay
so as you can see uh scenario is pretty
simple it locks in it verifies and then
locks out okay
and in the verification step you will
see that verification was successful uh
it is comparing the expected value with
an actual value okay
now if we look at the test case uh the
first step will open the URL or
application the second step is clicking
on the login link and then it is
entering the email password and taking
on login only difference uh in email and
password we are not using normal text
but we are using a configuration
parameter for both username and password
whose values are stored here okay
um then there's a verification step here
you will see I've used action mode
verify but I've used uh this particular
expression which is inner text equals
equals the configuration parameter of
username which will basically return me
the value of that configuration
parameter and then it will compare that
okay
so and then it is going to click on
logout and this is perfectly fine right
so there is nothing wrong in this
but you can make it more better okay a
better way of doing this is also using
the t-box evaluation tool okay
and let's see how we can do this
so here uh let's first disable this
particular step so if you don't know how
to disable a particular step you can
right click and then select disable okay
it will ask you for a reason and either
you can specify or you can leave it as
it is it has a timestamp and the
username who is disabling this okay
now um we are going to add our own step
here okay and I'm going to use the t-box
evaluation tool
right and this t-box evaluation tool is
going to sit here and let's change this
name as well okay so
I will say compare values or compare
email
okay and in this expression you can see
action mode is by default verify and
expression we need to pass two values
and the comparison operator okay so one
of our values we know it's our
configuration parameter for username but
the other value is not the inner text of
the username I want to capture the value
of that particular control in a variable
and then I'm going to make a comparison
between that variable and the
configuration variable okay
so let's do that for that I would
require another particular step okay
where I can capture this particular
value so let's do that and I'm going to
add the module which is required for
this
okay and I'm going to drag it before my
compare email step here I'm going to say
buffer uh email okay
and then this is the control which I
need to buffer so I'm going to change
the actual mode to buffer and here I'm
going to provide a particular buffer
name okay so I'm going to provide email
right
and then coming to our expression so our
expression would be so buffer of email
right
and then equals equals configuration
parameter of username
so pretty simple comparison but as you
can see both are Dynamic expressions and
I'm comparing two Dynamic Expressions
here okay
so the scenario Still Remains same but I
have shown you two ways how you can
perform this automation on this
particular scenario okay
now let's run this test case and see
whether the result is still the same or
there is some problem okay
so let's run this and let me close this
window
so it's going to login and then it's
going to check for the username
but that seems to be a problem okay
and you will see this in log info it
will show you what's the exact reason it
is saying missing end of file
now looking at the error you may be able
to guess that it is maybe not able to
compare uh two expressions because of
the different characters special
characters which it has so you need to
also Escape if you are using any special
characters in your values okay
so what we need to do is we need to
provide here okay codes for both this
Expressions so that it can basically
Escape any special characters in your
values okay
now if we go ahead and try this again
this time it should pass but let's see
okay it's successfully logged out that
means
um the scenario has passed and if we
look at the comparison you can see uh
now the values are compared correctly
because we have escaped any special
characters in these two values okay so
it has evaluated to true that's what is
returned by the t-box evaluation module
okay and you can see here uh also we
have created a buffer email which has
got this particular value okay
so you can see
um how I'm trying to use different
things here in order to automate this
very simple scenario but it's one of the
most common scenarios which will face
for any web application so I've shown
you both ways how you can do this and it
should be very useful when you are
trying to use different t-box automation
modules which are provided by Tosca
right rather than rewriting your own
automation or designing it separately
right you can use or reuse this
automation modules which are already
provided by Tosca so that's all for how
you can compare different Dynamic
expressions using the t-box evaluation
tool